Guide to the Charles Laverty Papers AIA.074
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Charles Laverty Papers
1767-2015
1960-2010
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Laverty, Charles A.
AIA.074
61 Linear Feet in 8 record cartons, 114 manuscript boxes, 3 half manuscript boxes, and 3 flat boxes
1 VHS
341.2 kilobytes in 10 computer files
Charles A. Laverty (1930-2015) was a journalist and historian who was active in Irish republican organizations. His research interests included the participation of the Irish in American wars, particularly the Revolutionary War and the Civil War. He was a founding member of the Irish Brigade Association, an organization devoted to the history of the United States Army 69th Infantry Regiment, an historically Irish regiment created in 1849. The Charles Laverty Papers date from 1767 to 2015, with the bulk of the material dating between 1960 and 2010. The collection documents Laverty's research interests, his working life, his participation in Irish republican organizations, his family history, and his membership in historical organizations. The bulk of the collection consists of Laverty's research files on Irish soldiers in American wars, members of the United Irishmen and the Fenian Brotherhood who emigrated to the United States, and members of religious orders who served as medical personnel on battlefields. The collection also contains correspondence, clippings, photographs, paper and born-digital administrative documents, publications of Irish historical and republican organizations with which Laverty was associated, and a video recording of members of the Irish Brigade Association. Laverty's work as a journalist is documented mainly through his publication Automotive Week, a weekly newsletter on the automobile aftermarket. The collection also includes the papers of William V. Kennedy, an author and historian with an interest in the American Civil War.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Charles Laverty, 2015. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2015.007, 2015.071, and 2016.004.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series, as follows.
Series I. Biographical Material Series II. Business Records Series III. Irish Brigade, 69th Regiment Material Series IV. Research Files Series V. Historical and Political Organizations Files Series VI. William V. Kennedy Papers
Series II. Business Records and Series V. Historical and Political Organizations Files are arranged in alphabetical order by type of material or organization title. Series I. Biographical Material; Series III. Irish Brigade, 69th Regiment Material; Series IV. Research Files; and Series VI. William V. Kennedy Papers are arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
Custodial History
Donated by Charles Laverty, 2015. In 2011, Laverty was hospitalized and his papers were moved, without his supervision, from his office. In 2014, the collection was partly housed in a storage facility and in Laverty's room at a senior living facility, both in New Jersey. Prior to and following Laverty's death in October 2015, the collection was transferred to New York University in January, April, and October of 2015. It is not known who packed the collection prior to its transfer to NYU.
Related Archival Materials
New York Irish History Roundtable Records (AIA 018)
An oral history interview of Laverty can be found in the Ireland House Oral History Collection (AIA 030), Box 2 Folder 41.
An archived version of Laverty's website can be accessed through the Internet Archive's Wayback Machine at https://web.archive.org/web/2013*/irishamericanindex.com.
Scope and Contents
The Charles Laverty Papers date from 1767 to 2015, with the bulk of the material dating between 1960 and 2010. The collection documents Laverty's research interests, his working life, his participation in Irish republican organizations, his family history, and his membership in historical organizations. The bulk of the collection consists of Laverty's research files on Irish soldiers in American wars, members of the United Irishmen and the Fenian Brotherhood who emigrated to the United States, and members of religious orders who served as medical personnel on battlefields. The research files contain photocopies from 19th and 20th century books, periodicals, and maps, as well as photographs, correspondence, pamphlets, and notes collected and created by Laverty. He used these files to create a website containing biographies of Irish people who settled in the American colonies and the United States between the 17th century through the 19th century. Laverty's membership in the Irish Brigade Association and the New York Irish History Roundtable is well documented in this collection through correspondence with members, paper and born-digital business records, clippings and photographs documenting activities of both organizations, and publications of both organizations. Laverty's work as a journalist is documented mainly through his publication Automotive Week, a weekly newsletter on the automobile aftermarket, with a small amount of material documenting his work at McGraw-Hill in the 1950s. The collection includes correspondence between Laverty and his family, photographs of his parents and siblings, and clippings about his family's horse breeding business and his brother's soccer career. Laverty's interest and participation in Irish republican organizations is documented through letters to Laverty from Brian O'Higgins, founding member and president of Sinn Féin; correspondence, publications, and administrative documents from Laverty's participation in Clan na Gael, Irish Republican Publicity Bureau, and Irish Prisoners Aid Committee. The collection also includes the papers of William V. Kennedy, an author and historian with an interest in the American Civil War. These include articles by Kennedy on the military and Catholicism, his work with the Thompson Battalion Memorial Project Committee, his military career, and his lawsuits brought against the Army War College.
Biographical Note
Charles A. Laverty (1930-2015) was a journalist and historian who was active in Irish republican organizations. His research interests included the participation of the Irish in American wars, particularly the Revolutionary War and the Civil War. He was a founding member of the Irish Brigade Association, an organization devoted to the history of the United States Army 69th Infantry Regiment, an historically Irish regiment created in 1849. Laverty was born in Moy, County Tyrone, Ireland in 1930 and immigrated to the United States in 1948. He worked in journalism and in the publishing industry for over 50 years, writing for the New York Journal-American and working as an editor for automotive magazines and for the Department of Defense before acquiring and publishing the newsletter Automotive Week between 1975 and 2000s. He served in the United States Army between 1951 and 1953 and was a member of the Army Reserves's Special Forces from 1957 to 1970. Laverty served as the national secretary for Clan na Gael in the 1960s, the chairman of the Irish Brigade Committee in the 1960s and 1970s, and president of the New York Irish History Roundtable in the early 2000s. He was an active member of a number of other Irish-American history organizations and Irish political organizations.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Electronic Records Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Irish Americans -- History.; Ireland -- History -- 20th century.; Northern Ireland -- History -- 1968-1998; Historians -- United States.; Correspondence.; Publishers and publishing -- United States.; Cemeteries -- United States -- History; Laverty, Charles A.; Kennedy, William V.
- Series I. Biographical Material, 1927-2014; 3.3 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, and 1 flat box
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
  Scope and Contents
  This series documents Laverty's family history, his military service, and his personal life. Material documenting the Laverty family includes family correspondence, and clippings and photographs documenting both his father's horse breeding business and his brother's soccer career. This material dates from the 1920s through the 2000s and includes correspondence, photographs, clippings, and ephemera. Material documenting Laverty's time in the United States Army and the Army Reserves Special Forces dates from the 1950s through the 1960s and includes correspondence, training documents, photographs, and Laverty's personnel file. This material also includes newsletters for Army retirees, Special Forces retirees, and retiree organizations formed around Army bases at which Laverty was stationed, including Fort Monmouth in New Jersey. Material documenting Laverty's personal life consists of correspondence with friends from Ireland and the United States, and dates from 1948 to 2007.
  - Biographical Materials, 1948-2012 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family Materials, 1947-2014 (Box 1, Folder 1-13, Box 125, Folder 6, Box 120, Folder 6-8)
  - Horse Trading Materials, 1927-2013 (Box 1, Folder 14-18)
  - Military Service Materials, 1951-2010 (Box 1, Folder 19-24, Box 2, Folder 1-8, Box 120, Folder 3-4)
  - Moy Materials, 1965-2007 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1948-2011 (Box 2, Folder 10-14, Box 39, Folder 6-11, Box 120, Folder 1-2)
- Series II. Business Records, 1954-2010; 5 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons and 4 manuscript boxes
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by type of material or organization title.
  This series documents Laverty's working life in the journalism field, from the 1950s through the 2000s. Material includes McGraw-Hill publications featuring Laverty and material documenting Laverty's 30 years as publisher of the weekly newsletter, Automotive Week. The latter includes the newsletter, correspondence regarding its publication and subscriptions, correspondence and legal documents regarding the sale of the newsletter in the early 2000s, and copyright documents.
  - Automotive Week -- Copyright Files, 1978-2003 (Box 2, Folder 26-33, Box 3, Folder 1-14, Box 9, Folder 1-18, Box 10, Folder 1-33)
  - Automotive Week -- Correspondence, 1967-2010 (Box 3, Folder 15-22, Box 120, Folder 9-10, Box 121, Folder 1)
  - Automotive Week -- Financial and Legal Files, 1978-2004 (Box 3, Folder 23-35, Box 10, Folder 34-37)
  - Automotive Week -- Industry Files, 1987-2003 (Box 3, Folder 36-40, Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Automotive Week -- Newsletters, 1983-2010 (Box 2, Folder 15-25)
  - Automotive Week -- Testimonials, 1977-2000 (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
  - Early Career Materials, 1954-1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series III. Irish Brigade, 69th Regiment Material, 1861, 1945-2014; 12 Linear Feet in 26 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, and 1 flat box; 1 VHS; 168.5 kilobytes in 5 computer files
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by topic. The inventory lists box and folder numbers for an alphabetical range of topics in the Subject Files. Topics containing a large amount of material are listed individually.
  This series documents Laverty's almost 60 years of involvement with the Irish Brigade Association (IBA) and his interest in the 69th Regiment of the United States Army. Material in this series dates from 1861 through 2014, with the bulk of the material dating from the early 2000s. The material includes correspondence, newsletters, paper and born-digital business and subject files, print photographs, a video recording, and ephemera. The correspondence documents Laverty's involvement in the organization from its founding in the 1960s through his work as the organization's president in the early 2000s and includes correspondence between Laverty and members of Congress, librarians and archivists, historians, and other members of the IBA. The subject files document the organization's work to locate the graves of former members of the regiment, through correspondence with research organizations and cemeteries, and paper and born-digital lists compiled by Laverty of confirmed and unconfirmed grave sites in cemeteries in New York and other states. The business files consist of correspondence and notes regarding meetings and events planned by the IBA. The video recording contains footage of members of the IBA marching in the New York City St. Patrick's Day parade and the ephemera consists of ribbons from IBA events. Other topics covered by this series include articles and books written by and about the IBA and members of the regiment, Civil War reenactment events, members of religious orders who served as medical personnel with the regiment, and Laverty's personal interest in particular members of the Regiment, including Thomas Francis Meagher and James McKay Rorty. In addition to the IBA's newsletter, The Irish Volunteer, this series also includes newsletters published by the the 69th Volunteer Corps, and the Veterans Corps 69th Regiment.
  - Business Files, 1957-2011 (Box 30, Folder 1-19, Box 31, Folder 1-18, Box 32, Folder 1-17, Box 125, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1959-2010 (Box 18, Folder 10-12, Box 19, Folder 1-9, Box 20, Folder 1-12, Box 21, Box 22, Folder 1-2, Box 121, Folder 2-7)
  - Newsletters, 1988-2014 (Box 23, Folder 1-33, Box 24, Folder 1-29, Box 25, Folder 1-22, Box 26, Folder 1-10, Box 27, Folder 1-7, Box 28, Folder 1-5, Box 121, Folder 8-11)
  - Photographs, 1961-2011 (Box 22, Folder 3-9, Box 29, Folder 1-5, Box 121, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook, 1959-1964 (Box 128)
  - Subject Files -- Ad - Art, 1862, 1990-2010 (Box 33, Folder 1-5, Box 125, Folder 4)
  - Subject Files -- Articles and Books, 1945-2009 (Box 33, Folder 6-9, Box 34, Folder 1-7)
  - Subject Files -- Artif - Br, 1902-2002 (Box 35, Folder 1-15)
  - Subject Files -- Burials, 1962-2007
    - Digital Files, TW_AIA_074_ER_2
    - Paper Files (Box 35, Folder 16-26, Box 36, Folder 1-18, Box 121, Folder 13)
  - Subject Files -- Burk - Mit, 1990-2007 (Box 36, Folder 19-30, Box 37, Folder 1-30, Box 38, Folder 1, Box 121, Folder 14-15, Box 122)
  - Subject Files -- Mixed Soldiers and Regiments, 1861, 1959-2010 (Box 38, Folder 2-26, Box 39, Folder 1-5, Box 40, Folder 1-14)
  - Subject Files -- Mo - W, 1990-2011 (Box 40, Folder 15-22, Box 41, Folder 1-46, Box 42, Folder 1-37, Box 122, Folder 2-4)
  - Video recording, Undated (Box Shared Tamiment 058)
- Series IV. Research Files, 1767, 1805, 1957-2014; 35.5 Linear Feet in 81 manuscript boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, and 2 flat boxes
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by topic. The inventory lists box and folder numbers for an alphabetical range of topics. Topics containing a large amount of material are listed individually.
  This series documents Laverty's over 50 years of historical research, focused on the Irish in the United States and Irish-Americans. The main topics of this series include the role of the Irish in American wars, from the Revolutionary War through the Spanish-American War, with a focus on the Civil War; members of the United Irishmen and the Fenian Brotherhood who immigrated to the United States in the 19th century; and members of religious orders who served as medical personnel during the Civil War. Material in this series dates from 1767 to 2014, with the bulk of the material dating from the 1990s and 2000s, and includes notes, printouts from online sources and photocopies of primary and secondary sources with some notes, books and pamphlets, photographs, maps, correspondence, writings by Laverty, and 18th and 19th century documents purchased by Laverty. The bulk of the material consists of photocopies of biographical data from secondary and primary sources, with notations by Laverty, and lists of and notes on reference sources, including book and article titles, names of historical and research institutions, and names of people to contact regarding Laverty's research interests. Other material in this series includes lists and notes Laverty compiled from his research files to include in a project first conceived of as a five volume encyclopedia to be titled Encyclopedia of Irish-American Military History, and was later hosted on a website titled IrishAmericanIndex.com. Other topics of interest to Laverty were cemeteries, in particular grave sites and monuments to Irish and Irish-American soldiers and religious serving as medical personnel; Irish indentured servants in the American colonies; and all Irish settlements in the American colonies and the United States, in particular Cecil County, Maryland.
  - A, 1957-2014 (Box 43, Folder 1-59, Box 44, Folder 1-19, Box 122, Folder 20, Box 125, Folder 7)
  - B, 1957-2014 (Box 44, Folder 20-36, Box 45, Folder 1-48, Box 46, Folder 1-70, Box 47, Folder 1-58, Box 48, Folder 1-40, Box 56, Folder 11-12, Box 122, Folder 21-23)
  - Ca - Cel, 1957-2014 (Box 49, Folder 1-71, Box 50, Folder 1-33, Box 51, Folder 1-5, Box 56, Folder 10, Box 122, Folder 24-25)
  - Cemeteries, 1957-2014 (Box 54, Folder 29-51, Box 55, Folder 1-6, Box 56, Folder 1-9, Box 122, Folder 26)
  - Ch - Cu, 1957-2014 (Box 51, Folder 6-63, Box 52, Folder 1-78, Box 53, Folder 1-69, Box 54, Folder 1-28, Box 122, Folder 27-29, Box 123, Folder 1)
  - D, 1957-2014 (Box 57, Folder 1-54, Box 58, Box 59, Folder 1-51, Box 123, Folder 2-3)
  - Ea - Em, 1957-2014 (Box 59, Folder 52-61, Box 60, Folder 1-16, Box 61, Folder 1)
  - Encyclopedia of Irish-American Military History, 1957-2014 (Box 60, Folder 17-25, Box 123, Folder 4)
  - Eng - Fenc, 1957-2014 (Box 61, Folder 2-47)
  - Fenians, 1957-2014 (Box 61, Folder 48-50, Box 62, Folder 1-15, Box 63, Folder 1-21, Box 64, Folder 1-89, Box 65, Folder 1-26, Box 123, Folder 5)
  - Fes - Fu, 1957-2014 (Box 65, Folder 27-60, Box 66, Folder 1-55, Box 67, Folder 1-22)
  - G, 1957-2014 (Box 67, Folder 23, Box 68, Folder 1-81, Box 69, Folder 1-80, Box 123, Folder 6-7)
  - H, 1957-2014 (Box 70, Folder 1-49, Box 71, Folder 1-77, Box 72, Folder 1-26, Box 123, Folder 8-9)
  - I, 1957-2014 (Box 72, Folder 27-63, Box 73, Folder 1-69, Box 74, Folder 1-29, Box 75, Folder 1-58, Box 123, Folder 10-11)
  - J-K, 1767, 1805, 1957-2014 (Box 76, Folder 1-76, Box 77, Folder 1-49, Box 123, Folder 12-13)
  - L, 1957-2014 (Box 77, Folder 50-58, Box 78, Folder 1-69, Box 79, Folder 1-31)
  - Ma, 1957-2014 (Box 79, Folder 32-79, Box 80, Folder 1-51)
  - Mc, 1957-2014 (Box 82, Folder 10-108, Box 83, Folder 1-105, Box 84, Folder 1-29)
  - Me, 1957-2014 (Box 80, Folder 52-59, Box 81, Folder 1-75, Box 82, Folder 1-9)
  - Mil - Mixed Regiments, 1957-2014 (Box 84, Folder 30-73, Box 85, Folder 1-9, Box 123, Folder 14-15)
  - Mixed Research Projects, 1957-2014 (Box 85, Folder 10-16, Box 86, Folder 1-8, Box 87, Folder 1-7, Box 89, Folder 53, Box 124)
  - Mk - My, 1957-2014 (Box 87, Folder 8-13, Box 88, Folder 1-68, Box 89, Folder 1-52, Box 124, Folder 8)
  - Na - Num, 1957-2014 (Box 90, Folder 1-33, Box 91, Folder 1-27, Box 124, Folder 9)
  - Numbered Regiments, 1957-2014 (Box 118, Folder 1-37, Box 119, Folder 1-16, Box 126, Folder 23-24)
  - Nuns and Chaplains, 1957-2014 (Box 91, Folder 28-52, Box 92, Folder 1-23, Box 93, Folder 1-3, Box 124, Folder 10, Box 126, Folder 1, Box 127, Folder 4)
  - O, 1957-2014 (Box 93, Folder 4-44, Box 94, Folder 1-64, Box 95, Folder 1-62, Box 96, Folder 1-20, Box 126, Folder 2)
  - P, 1957-2014 (Box 96, Folder 21-69, Box 97, Folder 1-39, Box 98, Folder 1-15, Box 126, Folder 3-5)
  - Q, 1957-2014 (Box 98, Folder 16-23)
  - Ra - Ree, 1957-2014 (Box 98, Folder 24-38)
  - Reference Sources, 1957-2014 (Box 98, Folder 39-42, Box 99, Folder 1-10, Box 100, Box 101, Box 102, Folder 1-5, Box 126, Folder 6-7)
  - Reg - Ry, 1957-2014 (Box 102, Folder 6-18, Box 103, Folder 1-100, Box 104, Folder 1-63, Box 126, Folder 8-9)
  - S, 1957-2014 (Box 105, Folder 1-49, Box 106, Folder 1-28, Box 107, Folder 1-79, Box 108, Folder 1-4, Box 126, Folder 10-14)
  - T, 1957-2014 (Box 108, Folder 5-51, Box 109, Folder 1-30, Box 126, Folder 15-18)
  - Ul - United Irishman, 1957-2014 (Box 109, Folder 31-34)
  - United Irishmen, 1957-2014 (Box 109, Folder 35-54, Box 110, Folder 1-50, Box 111, Folder 1-28)
  - United K - Ur, 1957-2014 (Box 111, Folder 29-43)
  - V, 1957-2014 (Box 111, Folder 44-47, Box 112, Folder 1-8)
  - Wa - Wea, 1957-2014 (Box 115, Folder 3-80, Box 116, Folder 1-43, Box 126, Folder 19-20)
  - Website Research Files, 1957-2014 (Box 112, Folder 9-17, Box 113, Folder 1-9, Box 114, Folder 1-10, Box 115, Folder 1-2, Box 126, Folder 21)
  - Wel - Wy, 1957-2014 (Box 116, Folder 44-62, Box 117, Folder 1-48, Box 126, Folder 22)
  - Y, 1957-2014 (Box 117, Folder 49-58)
- Series V. Historical and Political Organizations Files, 1926, 1942-2014; 4 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 1 flat box; 172.7 kilobytes in 5 computer files
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by type of material or organization title. The inventory lists box and folder numbers for an alphabetical range of topics and titles. The New York Irish History Roundtable files consist of a large amount of material and is listed individually.
  This series documents Laverty's participation in numerous organizations related to his interests in history and Irish republican politics. Material in this series dates from 1926 to 2014, with the bulk of the material dating from 1980s through the 2010s and includes correspondence, ephemera, publications, news releases, and paper and born-digital administrative documents. Laverty's membership in the New York Irish History Roundtable (NYIHR) and the American Irish Historical Society is documented through correspondence between Laverty and members of both organizations, publications created by both organizations, and agenda and meeting minutes from NYIHR meetings. Irish republican organizations documented in this series include Sinn Féin, Clan na Gael, the Irish American Unity Conference, and multiple organizations devoted to the cause of Irish political prisoners during the 1970s and 1980s. Material in this series includes correspondence with members of these organizations, dating from the 1950s through the 2000s; newsletters and ephemera created by these organizations, dating from the 1960s through the 2000s; and internal memoranda dating from the 1950s through the 1960s.
  - A - Irish Famine, 1926, 1949-2012 (Box 4, Folder 8-50, Box 122, Folder 5-8)
  - Irish Freedom - New York H, 1946-2014 (Box 5, Folder 1-29, Box 125, Folder 5, Box 122, Folder 9-14)
  - New York Irish History Roundtable, 1987-2011
    - Digital Files, TW_AIA_074_ER_1
    - Paper Files (Box 5, Folder 30-38, Box 6, Folder 1-9, Box 122, Folder 15-17)
  - Northern - 1981, 1942-2008 (Box 6, Folder 10-22)
- Series VI. William V. Kennedy Papers, 1952-2002; 2.1 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 9 manuscript boxes, and 2 flat boxes
  Biographical / Historical